in this video we're going to talk about
the law of reflection
so what exactly is that what is its
state
the law of reflection states that the
angle of incidence
is equal to the angle of reflection so
as an example let's say if we have a
flat surface
and let's say this is the normal line
which is perpendicular to the surface
and let's say if we have a light ray
that strikes the surface
at an angle of incidence of 30 degrees
the angle of incidence is between the
light ray and the normal line
according to the law of reflection
the ray is going to bounce back at the
same angle
so the angle of reflection which is also
between the normal line and the light
ray that's going to be 30 degrees
and so that's the law of reflection
now keep in mind these two angles are
complementary
the normal line always forms a right
angle with the surface
so this angle is 60 and this angle is
60.
now let's work on this problem a light
ray strikes the mirror at an angle of 30
degrees from the horizontal
what is the angle x where the ray leaves
the second mirror
so here this is the first mirror and
this is the second mirror
so this is the incident ray
and let's start by calculating the angle
of incidence
so we know that the normal line makes a
90 degree angle with
the surface
so these two angles add up to 90.
so 90 minus 30 is 60
and so that's the angle of incidence
and based on the law of reflection the
angle of incidence is equal to the angle
of reflection
so the angle of reflection for the first
mirror is also 60
which means this is 30.
now the three angles of a triangle
must add to 180
so what is this missing angle which
we'll call y
well 30 plus 130
plus y
is equal to 180
now 30 plus 130 is 160
and so now we need to subtract both
sides
by 160
so 180 minus 160 is 20
and so that's the missing angle here
so the angle of incidence for the second
mirror is going to be 90 minus 20 which
is 70.
and the angle of reflection for the
second row is 70 as well
which means x is 90 minus 70 so x
is 20 degrees
so that's the angle
that
the reflected ray
leaves the second mirror
so the angle of reflection for the
second mirror is 70 but the angle at
which it leaves the mirror is 20 which
is what we're looking for
you